<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An information for Mr. William Dell the (right reformer) as he is pleased to stile himself: (being the first to our best remembrance that ever assumed that title.) Or, An answer to his reply upon Mr. Loves contradictions. Together with the answer unto his epistle dedicatory to the Parliament. / By Umfrevile.</title>
            <author>Umfrevile, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95782</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing U26</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E367_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201269</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861795</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861795</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113940</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95782)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113940)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 59:E367[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An information for Mr. William Dell the (right reformer) as he is pleased to stile himself: (being the first to our best remembrance that ever assumed that title.) Or, An answer to his reply upon Mr. Loves contradictions. Together with the answer unto his epistle dedicatory to the Parliament. / By Umfrevile.</title>
                  <author>Umfrevile, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 7, [1] 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the better edification of Mr. Dels selected and peculiar people.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A confutation of Master Dells reply unto Master Loves contradictions (as he is pleased to terme them)" (caption title) has separate pagination; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Dell, William.  Right reformation (Wing D927).</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb: 24".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dell, William, d. 1664. --  Right reformation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Love, Christopher, 1618-1651 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113940:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN INFORMATION FOR M<hi rend="sup">R.</hi> WILLIAM DELL THE <hi>(RIGHT REFORMER)</hi> As he is pleaſed to ſtile himſelf: (being the firſt to our beſt remembrance that ever aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that TITLE.) OR, An Anſwer to his Reply upon Mr. <hi>LOVES</hi> CONTRADICTIONS. Together with the Anſwer unto his Epiſtle Dedicatory to the <hi>PARLIAMENT.</hi> By Umfrevile.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the better edification of Mr. <hi>Dels</hi> ſelected and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar people. 1646.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:113940:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113940:2"/>
            <head>AN ANSVVER UNTO M<hi rend="sup">R.</hi> WILLIAM DELL THE <hi>RIGHT REFORMER</hi> His Epiſtle Dedicatory TO THE PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, your Epiſtle, <hi>Janus</hi>-like, hath two faces, one looks to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Parliament, to make them yours, the other to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward your ſelves to make yours theirs; in your Sermon you break their heads, in your Epiſtle you binde them up: You flatter them with a ſeeming voluntary acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their power, and your free ſubmiſſion thereunto; in your aſſertion of the power of the Goſpel, you utterly enfeeble it: how
<pb facs="tcp:113940:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:113940:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:113940:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:113940:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:113940:5"/>comes it I pray to paſſe, that the juſt power of Magiſtracy is not conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent with the Kingdome of Chriſt? and why may not the one ſupport the other? ſeeing that both ought to be held of Divine Right and inſtitution, <hi>Touch not mine anointed,</hi> by all the expoſſions of the beſt that ever expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, is meant of both.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>Dell, q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ore,</hi> with what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ce durſt you terme the Presbyterian Government (not onely here eſtabliſht by Authority of the High Court of Parliament, but made choyce of, erected, conſtituted, embraced, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained and ſubmitted unto, from the very dawning of the Goſpel, and departure from <hi>Romes</hi> Idolatry, by all the Reformed Churches of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, as, That of <hi>France, Germany, Scotland,</hi> the <hi>Netherlands, Poland, Sweadland, Geneua, &amp;c.</hi> who all <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na voce,</hi> have approved of this Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and Government as the moſt conſonant to the word, and moſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the Romiſh Hierarchie (in that none but Prieſts ruling the Roſt, this conſiſting of a mixed temper, of Miniſters and Lay-Elders, one poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and balancing the too much powerfull influence of the other.) How durſt you, I ſay, give the reignes ſo farre unto your Anarchicall paſſion, or rather fury, as to call the ſaid Government, <hi>The laſt prop of Antichriſt in this Kingdome?</hi> yea, and that to the very face of thoſe that were by their power, not onely the promoters, but onely erectors of it: Hath the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, Mr. <hi>Dell,</hi> no better credit with you, than to be eſteemed the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectors of the <hi>laſt prop of Properie in this Kingdome,</hi> for theſe ſix years ſpace? <hi>Tantum ſudavit &amp; alſit,</hi> in the pulling down of Popery, and of late, in lieu of recompence have they given it <hi>new props?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truely Sir, I fear me, very few of that honourable Houſe, like no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of your Epiſtle then they did of your Sermon: if any doe, I muſt needs confeſſe that I feare it the more: and whether a man may more wonder at Mr. <hi>Dells</hi> impudence or ignorance, I cannot ſay, who indevoureth to indeare the Parliament unto him, by ſcandalizing and diſparaging the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment now generally thorough-out the whole Kingdome eſtabliſhed by them, and not that <hi>temerè &amp; ex improviſo,</hi> but after long demurring, ſerious conſultation, deliberate debate, neither without the advice and counſell of the beſt and choyceſt Divines throughout the Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and eſpecially of the Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> our united Brethren; and the better to gaine credit unto his deſigne, Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> doth his utmoſt to increaſe the diſlike, that ſome perhaps in the Parliament might have againſt this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſetled Government, he ſticks not to write that it threatens even the Parliament to diſpute its ſuperiority with them, and to make the ſupreme
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113940:5"/>Magiſtracy of the Kingdome to ſtoop under their lore.</p>
            <p>Who would have thought that after ſo much talk in the Sermon <hi>Of the enlargement of Chriſts Kingdome, of the exaltation of the Goſpel of Chriſt; the Word of Faith, Truth, and many the like good things;</hi> he ſhould fall to ſuch a malicious falſehood, in the <hi>Epiſtle Dedicatory?</hi> charging it with an aime at a power Paramount and predominant over the firſt Conſtitutors and Voters of it; which how farre ſwarving from truth, let all men judge who have either known or obſerved the behaviour of ſuch, that by electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on have been intereſſed in the Presbyterie, whether Miniſters or Laicks, let their deportment, I ſay, be duly conſidered, in what dutifull reſpective manners it ever hath been toward this High Aſſembly, not leaving ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted the Venerable Aſſembly of Divines, who never yet concluded any thing to be publiſhed concerning Reformation either in Church matters, or in manners, but in all humility they firſt preſented it to the view of the Honourable Houſe, attending uſually at the Houſe of Commons doore, and in their <hi>Theſes</hi> ſubmitting themſelves ſometimes to alteration, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation, alwayes unto approbation of the Honourable Houſes: which I dare affirm Mr. <hi>Dell,</hi> will not avouth that his Independent, and the reſt rabble of Sects that crowd themſelves under that name, either have done, or are about to doe, for then I think we ſhould hardly have ſuch diverſity of Conventicles and diverſities of Faiths breached in them by approve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Parliament, as at this day we have, ſo notoriouſly known unto all: That in one ſtreet in <hi>London</hi> every Childe ſhall lead you to three; And where you ſhall have ſuch ſtuffe commended to you, by way of Divine inſpiration, to be beleeved and taken up as dogniatical points of Faith, and with a <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (none of Gods children, not comprehended in the But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery ſcrowle of election in caſe of refuſall) That a man which hath onely the uſuall knowledge of the ordinary principles of Chriſtian Religion, if not out of mockage, yet out of a feeling compaſſion, muſt needs ſay, having heard them; Surely the blinde leads the blinde into the ditch.</p>
            <p>Another paſſage in Mr. <hi>Dells Epiſtle Dedicatorie</hi> is this:</p>
            <p>He likes not the ſpirituall power ſupporting by the temporall; it is An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti-Chriſtian he ſaith and Papiſticall; Mr <hi>Dels</hi> aſſertion ſmels not much of antiquity, (as neither his Sect) for he may read in the Annals of the Chriſtian Prinitive Church, long before any point of Popery was hatched, that men notable for ſanctity in thoſe times did paſſionately implore the aid and inte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>miſe of the ſword temporall toward the defence of the true Chriſtian verity, and the depreſſing, yea, extirpating of known Hereſies, as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113940:6"/>in the buſineſſe of that Arch-Heretick <hi>Arius</hi> (and ſome that are of the Independent crue hold the ſame damnable tenents, or elſe they have much wrong) all men know that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great interpoſed his authority more then in any thing elſe, and not onely his authority but his Paines, in the extinguiſhing and condemning of that Hereſie, or otherwiſe it had ſpread its contagion farther, and with a more peremptory Vogue: and moreover if there had beene nothing worſe found among the late Biſhops, then that ſaying, no Biſhop no King, nor more diſpleaſing to God, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaching the progreſſe of the Goſpell, for ought I know they might have ſtood ſtill, although Maſter <hi>Dell</hi> may be pleaſed to be put in minde that he whoſe familiar ſpeech it was, (no Biſhop no King) was no Biſhop but a King, and a King the very Paragon for learning and wiſedome of all thoſe this Iſland ever ſaw: a Prince that was of opinion, that the licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous liberty of Sectaries would produce as much danger to temporall Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy and State Government, as ever could or would the <hi>Pontiſiciall Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie,</hi> both agreeing in the pulling downe of civill Magiſtracie, though differing about the manner: and let Maſter <hi>Dell</hi> be told that the interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the civill power, or the requeſting the aſſiſtance of the ſame, in the maintenance of the undoubted faith of Chriſt, or an externall Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticke diſcipline, conſonant to the ſame (without which it is impoſible for the Orthodox doctrine long to conſiſt, diſcipline being the nerves and ſinnews by which a Church ſtands, as the doctrine, the food by which it is fed and nouriſhed) is neither the head nor the toe of Popery.</p>
            <p>And let me be bold to ask Maſter <hi>Dell</hi> one queſtion, to what purpoſe tends his large invective againſt the Presbyteriall Government now ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted? what, to have none? I could not be ſo ill perſwaded of tho man: whether then? marry to withdraw the Parliaments countenancing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection from the Presbytery, and to place it upon them, that is the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging of the <hi>power of Chriſts Kingdome,</hi> the exaltation of <hi>the Goſpell of Chriſt, the propagation of the elect people,</hi> which I ſuppoſe the good man meanes: loe then ſee all well. May it pleaſe the Parliament to Vote down the Presbytery, as <hi>the laſt prop of Papory in this Kingdome,</hi> for interlacing it ſelfe with the temporall power, and craving its aid and ſuccours againſt thoſe that would bring in aparchicall confuſion, firſt into the Church, then into the ſtate, and <hi>eadem opera,</hi> let them be pleaſed to Vote Maſter <hi>Dels</hi> choſen flocke the onely <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and his Government of Gods Church; (if he knew firſt himſelfe what it were or ſhould bee) let the Honourable Houſes, I ſay, but be pleaſed to doe thus, and behold, <hi>omnia
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113940:6"/>bene, the power of Chriſts Kingdome mightily enlarged, the exaltation of the Goſpel wonderfully furthered, &amp;c. hinc illa lacryma,</hi> now I perceive what makes the world flocke ſo faſt unto Independency; what power or autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſoever ſupports them, ſtands for the enlargement of the power of <hi>Chriſts Kingdome, the exaltation of the Goſpell,</hi> the Priviledges of Chriſts choſen people, for the beauty of Saints, and what not? but let them beware that ſeek for ſupportation, not onely againſt them, but even by them, they are at leaſt, but the laſt prop of Anti-Chriſt in this Kingdome: who would wonder if all the world now turne Independent? ſeeing that one that depends on them may better ſteale a horſe, then a man of another minde looke over the hedge: but to be more ſerious, the baddeſt actions have ever made ſhew of the beſt pretenſions, the fouleſt Hereſies have ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led themſelves by the moſt ſpecious titles; the Arians would be called by no other name but Catholick, although their curſed Blaſphemie impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the maineſt point in all Chriſtianity: it is an old ſaying, the Devill doth never ſhew his Cloven-foot at firſt; Schiſme is like the Panther, whoſe skin being of a ſweet ſent, and beautifull ſpotted colour, whereby he draws many other beaſts toward him, which approaching neare, are forthwith affrighted with the uglineſſe of his head; wherefore the better to be maſter of his prey, he diſcovers not that till he have them in his power: it is a truth infallible, that Schiſmes and Faction evermore in their firſt riſing put on the face of woman, but in their growth that of a lyon: the behaviour of the Anabaptiſts at <hi>Magdeburg</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> though long ſince, yet by reaſon of other Sects in theſe our dayes, not much different in opinions, and leſſe in practice, is a freſh revived in our memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; good God, what Sanctity, piety, humility, ſimplicity did thoſe Jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers ſhew at firſt? what charity and contempt of worldly mucke? ſo that they drew the whole Generality of the City after them, with the ſelfſame ſaying in their mouths which ſometime the <hi>Samaritans</hi> uſed toward <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus,</hi> ſurely theſe men are the great power of God; at length when their poore deceived proſelites began to grow numerous, they poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt them that the power of the civill magiſtrate was Heatheniſh and Anti-Chriſtian; that Chriſts true Diſciples muſt be all equall; neither were they defective in alleadging Scripture for this their project, ill under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood and worſe applyed. <hi>Christs Kingdome is not of this world ſay they, he that will be the greateſt amongſt you, let him be as your ſervant; the Kings and Princes of the earth beare rule, and exerciſe</hi> power over them, <hi>but with you not ſo. Doe not rich men trouble you, bringing you into judgement ſaith St.</hi> James.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113940:7"/>What concluſions draw they from theſe texts? why ſurely that all civill Magiſtracy is Anti-Chriſtian, (though thoſe that bare it at that time in that towne were known to be zealous maintainers of the Goſpell) it muſt have nothing to do with Gods choſen; they that did deſire to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by it in matter of faith, or for their better ſtrengthning did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt the countenance of the ſame toward the bearing up of the Church diſcipline eſtabliſhed in that famous City: from theſe infuſions what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows? The Comminalty riſeth againſt their lawfull Magiſtrates; not onely degrades them but butchers them; next the Miniſters drinke of the ſame cup, for no other fault, but that fearing the ſtorme approaching, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſing the civill Magiſtracy of its growth and proceeding, they beſought them for the ſuppreſſing of this ſwelling faction, and upholding of the anciently ſetled Government in that Church; but becauſe they ſought the maintenance of the lawfull Eccleſiaſtick Government by the civill ſword (which then was a toe or a finger of Anti-Chriſt, as it is now) therefore they taſted of the ſame ſawee with them: but what did the good Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts after this? what did they not? but to particulariſe what the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory mentioneth, they fell afterwards upon their owne proſelites, cut the throates of them, ſeized not onely the goods of all Citizens, but the ſtate it ſelfe, brought a text of Scripture to warrant it, though themſelves would be thereof the expoſitors, The <hi>meek ſhall inherit the Earth:</hi> This ſtory wants no application. Men muſt not look ſo much upon the words and ſhews as the practices of raiſers of factions; and as touching Maſter <hi>Dell,</hi> although thorough the whole courſe of his Sermon there is great talke of the ſpirit of meekneſſe, the ſpirit of humility, obedience, and the like; and in the cloſe of his Epiſtle Dedicatory, much aſſurance offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto the Parliament of his utmoſt endeavours, in relation to obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to their authority; yet ſee how Maſter <hi>Dell</hi> hath thwarted both, in his practice; he virulently laſheth Maſter <hi>Love,</hi> twits him in the teeth, <hi>with his diſcerning people,</hi> chargeth him <hi>with menaciny</hi> of the Parliament in caſe of deſertion from them, puts him in the number of the fingers and toes of Anti Chriſt: this action of Maſter <hi>Dell</hi> daming expreſly the party rather reſcents of nature then grace, of gall then meekneſſe, of malice then charity; nay, rather then Maſter <hi>Dell</hi> will miſſe to laſh him, he will hazard the reputation of the cloſe to his Epiſtle, and venters the queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his obedience to the Parliament ſo vehemently and ſeriouſly by him proteſted: for doth Mr <hi>Dell</hi> print his ſermon in obedience to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Houſe? I am given to underſtand the contrary; that the Houſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113940:7"/>ordered him neither thankes nor order to print it, but forbid both: yet Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> out of an humble obedience, if not to them, yet to Chriſt, will print it, and with an Epiſtle Dedicatory to the Houſe alſo: to ſpeak <hi>bonaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de</hi> and <hi>ſublata larva,</hi> I think three were the cauſes that prevailed with Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> to print his Sermon, though miſliked, though forbidden.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that he might be before-hand with Mr. <hi>Love</hi> in the Preſſe, though he had had the precedency of him in the Pulpit, and to foreſtall mens judgements, both toward him and his Sermon, a thing much practiſed in this claſhing Age, to cry whore firſt. The ſecond reaſon of the Printing of his Sermon was his zeale, to ſhew his diſlike in the Preſſe, as he had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten done before in the Pulpit of the Presbyterian form and Rule, as a <hi>prop of popery,</hi> and obſtacle to the <hi>inlargement of the Kingdome of Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> deſiring rather then that (or any other ſhould ſtand) there might be none at all, and ſo the peculiar people may doe and live as they liſt, who ſhould controll them that have the ſpirit of illumination and inſpiration <hi>ad nutum?</hi> yet this puts me in minde of what I read in one place of <hi>Samuel, And then there was no King in</hi> Iſrael, what follows? <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nusquiſque fecit qued fibi viſum fuerit,</hi> Every one did what was right in his own eyes, and that was wrong enough I beleeve. The third reſpect, for which Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed this Sermon, was, I beleeve, becauſe he was not licenſed by the Houſe to publiſh it, Nor no thanks returned him for it, Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Trade wind of his Faction, muſt needs doe it the readier for that; and reaſon enough he had to put him forward, for his party hath never gained more credit than by croſſing Authority: And had Mr. <hi>Dells</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe been ſuch that might have been thought worthy to have been Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed by the Houſe, it would never have purchaſed him that repute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his as now it hath; for nothing is cryed up amongſt them, <hi>Niſi quod nititur in vetitum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what meanes Mr. <hi>Dell,</hi> by that pathetick Latine Theme in the foot of the frontiſpiece to his book? <hi>Theologum me crede in regno veritatis natum, ero itaque, &amp;c.</hi> What reaſon had Mr. <hi>Dell, tam gravem proferre ſententiam in materia tam levi;</hi> Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> gives the Alarm here, <hi>tanquam Annibal ad portas,</hi> as if all were in danger to be loſt, true piety trampled under foot, true Religion baniſhed, Chriſts Kingdome vanquiſhed, unleſſe all ſtrike ſale unto Independency, whereof he profeſſeth himſelf an aſſerter <hi>ad wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem &amp; ſanguinem uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi> I find in all ages that all Innovators are of <hi>Bruce</hi> his temper, <hi>quicquia volunt valdè volunt;</hi> rather then they will want their wills, <hi>Coelum terra miſcendum.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:113940:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113940:8"/>
            <head>A Confutation of Maſter DELLS Reply unto Maſter LOVES Contradictions (as he is pleaſed to terme them).</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>After <hi>Dell</hi> Prologues in butter and honie, puts Maſter <hi>Love</hi> in great hopes of his conſcientious dealing: <hi>He will not wrong him</hi> (forſooth) <hi>in any meaſure, in what he ſaid, and</hi> to th'end he might not, he ſpares not to ſet downe the warranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble courſe he tooke, he would not truſt his owne memorie (that might have bin as weake as his wits) therefore he repaires to one who tooke Maſter <hi>Loves</hi> notes in ſhort hand, <hi>Honeſtaratio, tis faire</hi> hetherto: But will Maſter <hi>Dell</hi> ſay and hold? doth he wrong Maſter <hi>Love</hi> in no manner of way throughout his reply? no, not in the very paring of his nailes; not in a little vinegar language? No ſure; they may beleeve that will: but they that ſhall obſerve divers paſſages in his ſtrong <hi>Polymickes,</hi> muſt needs confeſſe that Maſter <hi>Dell</hi> falls three farthings in a penny: but <hi>ad rem.</hi> Maſter <hi>Love</hi> ſaith (and he ſaith true) that the begun reformation is cryed down with confidence by ſome that would have neither that nor any other ſetled and firmely eſtabliſhed to which the whole nationall Church ſhould ſubmit: to this Maſter <hi>Dell,</hi> being <hi>Lupus in fabula,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd by the verdict of his own Conſcience, as thoſe that are told of in the Goſpel man by man til the woman was left alone knowing himſelfe not only one, but the Maſter one of thoſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113940:9"/>Maſter <hi>Love</hi> meant (as of purpoſe he would make it knowne to all the world, in his late worthy Sermon) Enters the liſt, takes up the bucklers, and replies in this manner. <hi>That the Kingdome of Chriſt is Spirituall,</hi> the Reformation of it anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable: That Maſter <hi>Love hath bin ſo blind or worſe as to affirme that the Preaching of the Spirituall and glorious Reformation is to preach againſt all Reformation.</hi> Is Maſter <hi>Dell</hi> ſo madiſh, fooliſh, knaviſh or worſe, as to charge Maſter <hi>Love</hi> with ſuch a notorious falſehood? Is not Maſter <hi>Love</hi> knowne to be as Jealous, painefull, laborious and active in th'advancing the kingdome Spirituall of Chriſt as he? Hath he not preſſed the glorious Reformation as farre as hee? Is Maſter <hi>Dell</hi> either ſo maſiciouſly ignorant or ignorantly malicious that he ſhould not bluſh to write that Maſter <hi>Love</hi> affirmes, <hi>That the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which Jeſus Chriſt works in the faithfull by his Spirit is no Reformation at all?</hi> Is your ſottiſhnes ſo braſend that it durſt commit ſuch a Signall ſcandall to the Preſſe touching a brother and fellow Miniſter in the Goſpell? When Maſter <hi>Love</hi> preacht for outward Reformation and a ſetled decent viſible Government in the Church did he preach againſt the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward? Or in the judgement of all underſtanding, learnd, honeſt and pious men is it not <hi>inordine</hi> to the Inward? When Maſter <hi>Love</hi> deſervedly ſpake againſt your <hi>Chymericall</hi> whimſes, puſht he at the gracious operation of Chriſt in the heart of any particular man, thinke yee? Sir, Maſter <hi>Love</hi> averreth that you (as all that know you, know you doe) op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe at outward civill diſcipline in the Church: thats his aime, your reply hath nothing unto this, quitting you of this imputation: (Yow know it ſits to faſt to you to be ſhaken off) but inſtead of clearing your ſelfe of this, you clap a falſe aſperſion upon Maſter <hi>Love,</hi> and which is <hi>Nihil ad Rombum,</hi> as wide as <hi>Yorke</hi> from <hi>London,</hi> from a reply <hi>ad oppoſitum,</hi> That he forſooth denies Spirituall Reformation; well replide Maſter
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113940:9"/>
               <hi>Dell,</hi> to what Maſter <hi>Love</hi> contradicteth not, you have retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a very able reply (Let able men judge of it) but to what Maſter <hi>Love</hi> contradicteth indeede, you reply nothing at all. Maſter <hi>Love</hi> contradictes your chalke, you would choake him with your reply in cheeſe; Maſter <hi>Dell</hi> you ſhall be no replier for me. Maſter <hi>Love</hi> informed that Honorable Audience no more then the world knowes, that you not only ſnarle and barke at, but would bite and reare in peeces all <hi>Chriſtian Civill</hi> Diſcipline and Church Regiment if you could; Maſter <hi>Love</hi> proceeds, and tells you as if all were comprehended within the narrow heart of man: and very well truly, for if every mans heart may paſſe for his owne acquittance, and none ſhould judge and controule our outward converſation and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour but our ſelves, men would quickly have the title of the play in their mouthes, <hi>A mad world my Maſters;</hi> But to this Maſter <hi>Dell</hi> replies. When the heart is reformed all is reformed (from top to toe, no ſuch matter, Maſter <hi>Dell,</hi> though the heart be reformed, yet all may not be reformed. Maſter <hi>Love</hi> accuſeth you rightly enough yet: Maſter <hi>Dell,</hi> men may obſerve in theſe times as bad beleevers and good men (namely many Religious and Votaries as they call them in the Church of Roome, both men and women, divers of them leading moſt innocent and harmeleſſe lives, and which if the roote from which they ſpring were right, might juſtly be tearmed holy.) So on the contrary, true beleevers, and none of the beſt livers. Some wonderfully I dare ſay enlightned yea and inſpired with the Spirit of God, who I will be bold to ſay had from God a large ſhare of ſaving Graces, I and in whole hearts (I write it with confidence) the <hi>Spirituall king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt</hi> was certainly by himſelfe erected: Yet of their living very looſe that I may not ſay ſcandalous: as theſe men paſſe downe the ſtreames of this life and in the ſtearing of their courſe approach too neare the Anchors or
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113940:10"/>Sands of offence: whereby they are in danger to be either ſplit by the one, or Swallowed up by the other; would not the publicke and viſible Boye of diſcipline eſtabliſhed in the Church point unto theſe men the true Chanell of a righter, and ſafer converſation? and ſhall we bring a Text or two of Scripture to confirme this? Our Saviour in the Goſpell, as touching an obſtinate and refractorie brother, ſaid to us ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly <hi>dic Eccleſiae,</hi> and in caſe of refuſall to ſubmit in all du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull obedience unto it, whether for admonition or cenſure, (according to the nature of the failing) <hi>Sit tibi tanquam Ethnicus et Publicanus.</hi> What is this Church but the choſen and ſelected members, the heads of the Tribes (as I may ſo call them) men Eminent for pietie, and Signall abilities of government and diſcretion, which are conſtituted and ſet up by the whole Chriſtian Congregation and Aſſemblie, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nationall or Provinciall, <hi>Ad cauſas cognoſcendas,</hi> to judge of order, direct, reforme, yea, &amp; cenſure too if need ſo require, the exorbitant ſwarvings of their inferior and younger bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren? and what meanes (<hi>Dic,</hi> tell) but complaine? if no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther remedy, if private admonition will not ſuffice, <hi>ſi longius Serpit malum,</hi> if he proceedes in <hi>detrimentum totius,</hi> if by his ſtife-neckedneſſe others alſo may or do fall into careleſneſſe, Why, <hi>Dic Eccleſiae ut Curet illa ne res-publica Chriſtiana inde damno afficiatur;</hi> that the ſinnews of the Churches body be not thereby looſen'd.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> in the cloſe of one of his Epiſtles gives expreſſe order <hi>to marke ſuch as walked diſorderly.</hi> What meant he by thoſe words <hi>(marke ſuch?)</hi> Surely, ſome Empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, ſome reſtraining coercive power was in them. But doth Maſter <hi>Dell,</hi> and his Peripatetick (Comrade, that <hi>(walking)</hi> I doe not ſay <hi>(Wandering light)</hi> Maſter <hi>Hugh Peters,</hi> the mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous new <hi>Goſpeller, That famous Centaure or Horſebacke Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher,</hi> do theſe two great Pillars of this late forged building (the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113940:10"/>
               <hi>new peculiar people of God</hi>) preſume to ſay and preach like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that they have no need of any outward Government they? Theſe men have no durt, no, not upon their clothes they, much leſſe in their skin: Gods choſen amongſt whom can be found neither blur nor blot they, and then I pray what need of any Church Government on them, I mean theſe Darlings and Favorites of God, who have as great an impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility from erring as the Pope: They are ſo farre in Gods bookes that they can hardly get out: <hi>Homines omni excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one Majores,</hi> they; I remember that ſometime the <hi>Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> boaſted, that they had not any Whores amongſt them: no by no meanes they: yet by the Lawes of their State they were permitted <hi>Concubitum promiſcuum,</hi> every man to hold his Neighbours wife as deare as his owne, and ſo in honeſt plaines they were all Whores: I will forbeare application at this time.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Love</hi> infers the racing our the firſt Article of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant from Mr. <hi>Dells</hi> poſitions, if they took place: and well he might make ſuch an inference: for that Article obligeth me, beſides other things, to maintain a Diſcipline in our Church, conformable unto the Diſcipline of the beſt Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches of Chriſtendome, and namely, to that of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> to this Replies, <hi>That he had rather the whole Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant were raced out, then the leaſt truth contained in the word of God.</hi> Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> by theſe words, ſeems to have a minde to ſet Gods word and the Covenant together by the ears; as if they were <hi>oppoſita</hi> at the leaſt, if not <hi>contraria,</hi> that they could not both well cotten, and were Mr. <hi>Dells</hi> power as good as his will, I ſhould be loath to truſt him (<hi>foenum enim portat in cornu</hi>) but God ſends hungeing cattle ſhort hornes: this game is too ſtrong for Mr. <hi>Dell,</hi> he will give it over, (there may be danger in it) the Fox loves no Grapes, not he.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:113940:11"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> bath better remembred himſelf; complies, and tels you, <hi>That he likes the Covenant well enough;</hi> does he, does he? I am very glad of it: but ſtay, Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> hath not done yet, give him leave I pray to ſay out his ſay: Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> doth not like the Covenant <hi>abſolute &amp; ſimpliciter,</hi> he hath never a well, or well enough for it in that ſenſe: how then? why marry <hi>he likes the Covenant well enough, according to the true pretention of it:</hi> oh now I ſee the Aſſes ears, through the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons skin, for what I pray, was not this a principall intention of the Covenant, to linke the new Reformed Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> in the bend of unity, not onely of Doctrine, but alſo of outward Diſcipline and Government, with the beſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches of Chriſtendome, and namely with that of our brethren of <hi>Scotland?</hi> this I confeſſe <hi>aperta fronte,</hi> to be the intention of the Covenant; as it is plainely ſpecified in it. Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> doth he like it according to this intention? I fear not: Mr. <hi>Dell.</hi> may give the Covenant ſome conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on apart, as well as expound the Scripture a part, I mean in a ſublime illuminated inſpired way, never heard of before this day and erect a new people apart if it pleaſe him: But Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> muſt have a Reformation according to Gods Word, why is the Reformation ſetled by Covenant, not according to the word, and ſhall not more be found for it in the word, then for any other?</p>
            <p>It may eaſily be gathered from his diſcourſe: otherwiſe why doth he fall with ſuch a feud upon Maſter <hi>Love</hi> for maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Reformation ſuch as now it is eſtabliſhed by Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, telling him that <hi>he would reforme</hi> without the <hi>word, yea againſt the word, (Oh frons perfricta) Oh what aforchead hath this man! without any ſecular power,</hi> loe then what troubles Maſter <hi>Dells</hi> ſore eyes, he is diſeaſed to ſee the preſent Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in the Church bore up and ſupported by temporall and Secular power, he likes neither the ſupporters, neither
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113940:11"/>the ſupported: he would rather then his life make a rent the one from the other, Maſter <hi>Dell</hi> hath cond his leſſon <hi>divide et impera,</hi> he cannot thrive in his fiſhing except theſe waters be troubled, <hi>Illi quieta magna merces:</hi> and to effect this <hi>omnem movet lapidem,</hi> he ſpares not for falſehoods; firſt he tells Maſter <hi>Love</hi> that he reformes not <hi>only without, but againſt the Word; to bring</hi> Maſter <hi>Love</hi> out of conceite with the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he tells the Magiſtrate that <hi>the Presbutery</hi> will not ſuffer the power in their hands, but would faine tugge it out and get it into their owne and rule the roſt forſooth as they pleaſe) and thus he writes to withdraw the Magiſtracie from the Presbutery, and to put ſuſpition, if not envy into their heads, but to conclude this his third Reply: Doth not Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> read no where in the Prophet <hi>Eſay, Kings ſhall be thy nurſing Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and Queens thy nurſing Mothers?</hi> is not this ſpoken of the Church? and is not the meaning of that, the time ſhould come that the great Potentates of the earth ſhould maintain, cheriſh, ſupport, and countenance the outward profeſſion, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and diſciplinary exerciſe of the true Goſpel, (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which the Goſpel can have no ſure progreſſe (nay, no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute in the world) puniſhing, bridling, and mateing by their ſecular power, now in a ſpirituall and chriſtian hand, all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractary flyers out, all inordinate and extravagant oppoſers, either in dogmaticall points or manners?</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Love</hi> ſaith that Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> ſetting all things in order, that was a Church order, and ſure it was: to this our Replier ſpurs a queſtion, and demands what outward or ſecular power <hi>Paul</hi> had to ſet the Church in order: had Saint <hi>Paul</hi> none good Mr. <hi>Dell?</hi> Did Saint <hi>Paul</hi> exerciſe no outward power in the Church, during his abode upon the earth? read you not what order he gave unto <hi>Timothy</hi> concerning the choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Elders, and what his carriage ſhould be in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buking of an Elder?</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:113940:12"/>
            <p>Doth he not write unto the ſame <hi>Timothy,</hi> what Widdows he would have choſen in the Church, and what not? did he not ſharpely reprove the whole Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> in two matters? The firſt concerning their diſſolute behaviour in their comming to the Lords Table; the ſecond, for their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Law one with another, and the trying of their diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences before unbeleeving Judges, whence did accrue much ſcandall to the profeſſion of Chriſt, and did he not give ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe order for the redreſſe of both? and was this done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a powert and thinks not Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> that this power was likewiſe obeyed? or conceives Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> that all Chriſtians were haile-fellow well met with Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in point of ruling and directing in the outward face of the viſible Aſſemblies of the Church or doth Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> take that Text of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> for Apocrypha or no, Where the Apoſtle makes a <hi>Clymax,</hi> though not a <hi>Hierarchie</hi> in Government of the Church, ſaying that <hi>God had ordained ſome Doctors, ſome Paſtors, ſome Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in the church:</hi> and all for the building up of the body of Chriſt? if Mr <hi>Dell</hi> takes theſe words for Scripture, as I know not whether he will or no, ſure I am many of his Gang, have of late chalked through the Bible, what they will have goe for Scripture and what not, but if he admit of this paſſage of the Apoſtle for Scripture, he muſt needs grant that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of an outward viſible government in the Church, I mean amongſt men, and that for the building up, enlarging, not binding up the inviſible kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt in men: but I have not done with S. <hi>Paul</hi> yet, had he no outward pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the Church? no, To cry all Government down under heart Government, and all Reformation as carnall, becauſe the civill Magiſtrates hand is to it, is not only againſt the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2. Pray for Kings, &amp;c. but Mr. <hi>Love</hi> it is againſt all other places of his Epiſtle, Where upon occaſion he mentioneth the civill ſword, as namely that in <hi>Romans</hi> 12. where the Apoſtle diſputes at large the prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative of civill power,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113940:12"/>above the reſt, all others being delegative from him in his own Dominions. <hi>Obey the higher powers,</hi> ſaith that great St. <hi>Paul, becauſe none but of God. Therefore obey the King as chief, and Lord Paramont,</hi> and others as his Lieutenants. St. <hi>Paul,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the holy Ghoſt by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> ſticketh not to give reaſon of this obedience: <hi>He beareth not the Sword in vain.</hi> God hath not given it to him for nothing, he hath not committed it into his hand onely to contemplate it, to gaze upon it, <hi>Tanquam ignem in pariete depictum,</hi> no ſuch matter; he hath Commiſsion from God to put it in practice, to be active with it, <hi>Ad ſuſt inen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos bonos, ad coercendos malos:</hi> What returns Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> to this: Mr. <hi>Dell pro imperio ſuo</hi> doth not hold this contradiction of Mr. <hi>Love</hi> worth his reply. <hi>Non vacas exiguis rebus adeſſe Jovi, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quila non capit muſeas:</hi> 'twere a diſparagement for Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> to anſwer a contradiction ſo full of Chinks as this, and therefore he tranſmits <hi>This Mr. in Iſrael</hi> (Thus out of his abundant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect unto Mr. <hi>Love,</hi> and out of a conſcientious circumſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on not to wrong him in the leaſt meaſure, as he gives us to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand in his Prologue, he is pleaſed to flowt him) he puts him over, I ſay, to be anſwered by <hi>Babes and Sucklings:</hi> onely for his better inſtruction, he will vouchſafe to give Mr. <hi>Love</hi> the ſence of the Scripture impertinently alledged by him; for the holy Ghoſt (I take it) whiſpers <hi>The right Informer in the eare</hi> (as the Pigeon did ſometime the Impoſter <hi>Mahomet</hi>) all the right ſence of any place of Scripture, he needs not pump for the Expoſition of any difficult or knottie paſſage of the Bible, he, <hi>The right Informer,</hi> hath a priviledge from erring in expounding any text of holy Writ aſcribed to him <hi>ex aſſe: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocentius, Paulus, Vrbanus, Bonifacius,</hi> not any of <hi>Chriſts Vicars Generall</hi> ever had the like, no not <hi>è Cathedrâ,</hi> doth Mr. <hi>Dell, the right Informer,</hi> give the ſence, never doubt it, <hi>Ipſe dixit,</hi> tis out of hunger and cold: let us hear then from Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of that text wherein Mr. <hi>Love</hi> (he ſaith) was ſo groſly miſtaken that he is forced to turn him over unto babes and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113940:13"/>ſucklings for an Anſwer. <hi>Why, the evident ſence of that place is this</hi> (ſaith the Oracle) <hi>That Chriſtians ſhould pray for Kings and Governors, that God would ſo incline their hearts, that whileſt we live in godlineſſe under them</hi> (your godlineſſe is <hi>in late ſenſu</hi> Mr. <hi>Dell) they would ſuffer them to live in peace:</hi> (you will never live in peace (you) Mr. <hi>Dell;</hi> is it likely that a Sect which compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends under it <hi>omnium ſpeude dogmatum colluviem,</hi> a common ſhore of all what is naught, wil ever endure peace) <hi>and not make us fare the worſe in the world for our intereſt in the kingdom of God.</hi> Hath no body intereſt in the kingdom of God but you Mr. <hi>Dell?</hi> have you mor opolized Heaven? what mean you by <hi>(our) intereſt in the kingdom of God,</hi> ſo <hi>emphatice</hi> and <hi>excluſive</hi> ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken? but lets look a little nearer into this evident ſence Mr. <hi>Dels</hi> familiar hath given of that text, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2. why Kings and Governors muſt indeed be prayed for, but how? not ſo much for themſelves as for others: who are they? marry <hi>thoſe that have the onely intereſt to Gods kingdom;</hi> and who they are, or at leaſt whom is meant that they are, Mr <hi>Dell</hi> can tel you better then I: but may not <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Governors,</hi> eſpecially Chriſtian, that have ſubmitted their Scepters and Powers under the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of the Goſpel, given their names to Chriſt, be meant by the Apoſtle, to inforce godlineſſe? tis true Mr. <hi>Dell,</hi> to bend the heart, to carrie the minde, to kindle in the affections a true love of god lineſſe, to make the will ſtrike ſail unto it, that is beyond all humane reach, and onely <hi>opus altiſſimi:</hi> yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the earthly Powers may and ought to conſtrain all wilfull diſturbers, either of the ſound doctrine, or the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall wholeſome diſcipline of the Church, unto an open and outward Conformity with the Generall Aſſemblie, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, take ſuch courſe, that if they will do no good, they ſhall do no harm: This the Civill Power may do, And in ſo doing, doth greatly, no queſtion, for the welfare of the proſperitie of the Goſpel: and without all doubt, when the Apoſtle in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2. gives that charge of <hi>praying for Kings and all in Authority:</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:113940:13"/>his meaning was, that we ſhould pray that they might uſe eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry branch and limbe of their Authoritie to the furtherance not onely of Chriſts ſpirituall kingdom, but alſo of his viſible (and as I may ſo ſpeak) temporall kingdom (I meane the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of men openly profeſsing his Name) here upon earth; That they might exerciſe their Power directive, and prorective toward all that in quiet and humble obedience (in all outward appearance) ſtrooke ſail to the outward ordinance of preaching the Goſpel; and to the Generall received Diſcipline as the ſquare of their manners: towards the oppoſers, diſquieters, and open violaters of either of theſe, Kings and Governors ſhould uſe their power both coercive and vindictive: and that ſo they may do (without offence unto Mr. <hi>Dels</hi> evident ſence to the contrary) I am perſwaded by this text of the Apoſtle, I am both counſelled, exhorted, and warranted to beleeve.</p>
            <p>But yet before I have quite done with this Mr. <hi>Dels</hi> fift Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, I muſt dwell a little longer upon his <hi>evident</hi> ſenſe of that place; for to me it appears that Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> hath evidently ſhot at his own ends; and plaid his own game, and that of all his other Sectaries by ſuch a gloſſe. Mark then 2 things mainly conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in this his interpretation of that place. Firſt, that Kings and Governours are not to be prayd for <hi>gratia ſui,</hi> for their own ſakes, <hi>but onely that thoſe which have an intereſt in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt, may live in peace, and not ſare the worſe for them:</hi> as for praying for them any otherwiſe, either for their glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, victorious and proſperous Reign over us, for their ſucceeding poſteritie, that their Rule may be advantagious to the enlarging the viſible kingdom of Chriſt in the world, the better for the erecting the inviſible; to pray for Kings and Governours in this regard Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> holds it not needfull, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth the fore-named Text make for it.</p>
            <p>The ſecond to be obſerved in his commenting upon that Text, is, that the meaning is not that the Magiſtrate ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force godlineſſe, but <hi>protect us in godlineſſe:</hi> lo you there, all that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113940:14"/>a Civill Magiſtrate muſt do, muſt be onely to <hi>protect</hi> Mr. <hi>Dels</hi> peculiar people in godlineſſe: thats enough for him, he needs trouble himſelf no farther. But to ſtand for any ourward Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Politie, to maintain them that in order to the inward promotion of the Goſpel ſubmit to it: to ſuppreſſe (if no other mean will prevail) even by the power of the Sword, thoſe that (to the hazard of Chriſtian unitie, and reproach of the very Chriſtian faith) tumultuouſly and ſeditiouſly gainſay it: for the Civill Magiſtrate to put his hand to this, he doth <hi>ultra cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidam:</hi> Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> tels us plainly, that the Scripture, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.3. <hi>hath another evident ſence, viz. of protecting men in godlineſſe;</hi> (ſuch as every private Conventicle is pleaſed to ſet up) <hi>not the inforcing men unto godlineſſe,</hi> namely, to yeeld outward ſubmiſsion, quiet obedience, and filiall reſpect unto the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine publick taught, and diſcipline practiſed in the face of the viſible Congregations.</p>
            <p>They have no power for that, if Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> be a friend to the civill power, let thoſe be judges whom it moſt concernes; but it is a point of my creed, that thoſe that wonld exclude them in one, would juſtle them out of the other, laid it in their hands: ſtrange it is that order ſhould be commended tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough all the creation, order in the vegetive creature, for place the elements have their ſituation according to the nobleneſſe of their quality, order in the ſenſitive imployed and prized by men according to the valuation of their inſtincts, order in the rationall: men having callings, ſome to command, ſome to obey, according to the excellencies and advantages of gifts the one above the other: order in Heaven, there being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of perfection and glory given not onely to the Saints by God, but even unto the Angels themſelves, if not above yet beyond their fellows: order in all State-Government, Monarchicall, Ariſtocraticall, Demotraticall, yea amongſt the Turkes, Moores, Tartars, Indians, Perſians, Muſcovites,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113940:14"/>although Infidels or as bad, yet even in all their Idolatrous and vaine worſhip: they have ſome order which they hold, and by which they ſet the compaſſe of the miſtaken and blind devotion: nay there is order in Hell, that formidable place could not endure without order. If Satan be divided againſt himſelfe be cannot ſtand: even in Hell God holds an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in puniſhing, ſo then ſhall there be, is there an order u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſaliter thorough the creation and Gods triple Monarchy, and onely a Chaos of Anarchy and confuſion in the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his viſible body the Church? <hi>quis furor ocives quae tanta eſt dementia ſecli?</hi> if God be <hi>Deus ordinis</hi> the God of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and there can be no order without government: let all men ſee what maſter builders theſe are, and what worke they are likely to make, that deny outward government in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Church, without which it cannot ſubſiſt: your ſixt reply unto Mr. <hi>Loves</hi> Serm. <hi>tantum mutato nomine de te appri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me narrari poſsit,</hi> a covering fox <hi>your owne cup,</hi> for let <hi>your very babes and ſucklings be</hi> judge who juſtle out the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate. You that will acknowledge his power only in tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and call it the power of the Nations (in ſome oppoſition to that of Chriſts as I gueſſe) or thoſe that acknowledge it from heaven, to be very good as iſſuing from the fountaine of all goodnes, thoſe that earneſtly deſire the heart &amp; hand of a godly civil Chriſtian power, as a reſtorative for the ſouldring maintaining, and eſtabliſhing of all the outward members of the viſible company into one compacted perſpicuous building who moſt juſtles out the Magiſtrate, he that acknowledgeth his power both in Church and State; or he that <hi>clara voce</hi> denies either that <hi>de jure,</hi> he ſhould have, or <hi>de facto</hi> ever had power in the one (both groſſe untruths) and but faintly grants it in the other? Good Sir, aſcribe not your own work to our hands, ſet the ſaddle where it ſhould be: Good Sir, have you not made it a chiefe part of your buſineſſe now for a long
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113940:15"/>
               <hi>while together: Have you not openly vaunted in your Preſſes and Pulpits, that you have had the chieſeſt ſhare in laying Monarchicall Government in the duſt? Did you, I mean the Independent Tribe, not brag, and openly crack it in Taverns, Ordinaries, and where not, that God had made you the head Inſtruments of quelling the Kings power?</hi> And I am bodily afraid that you are diligently acting how you may put your work in a forwardneſſe to deal with the other. I heard a Bird ſing a very ſtrange note from New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Caſtle, if I may be ſo fortunate as to get the dictie for your ſatisfaction, I ſhall not ſpare to publiſh it. <hi>Now becauſe you would not be miſtruſted your ſelves in caſting off the yoke of the Civill Power in reference unto Church Diſcipline, you publickly ſlander the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, for tugging it out of their hands, and getting all into their own.</hi> We ſee clearly through all your ſlender devices Mr. <hi>Dell,</hi> in his 7. Reply to what Mr. <hi>Love</hi> quoteth out of <hi>Ezra</hi> 7.26. that <hi>who would not do the Law of God and the King, ſhould be ſpeedily executed:</hi> To this Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> replies, <hi>more ſuo,</hi> far wide of the intention either of his Adverſarie, or King <hi>Artaxerxes:</hi> for Mr. <hi>Love</hi> to prove that the Temporall Power hath to do with the conſtitution or ſtabliſhment of the viſible Church, brings this place of <hi>Ezra</hi> to confirm it, and well to the purpoſe, now pray heare with what Expoſition Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> is inſpired (from a ſpirit I wot) as touching the force of this place. <hi>Firſt that the Magiſtrate may make a Decree for all that are minded of their own free will to build the ſpirituall Temple of Jeſus Chriſt, &amp;c. Riſum teneatis amici?</hi> Would you not pardon any man, Mr. <hi>Dell,</hi> that ſhould take the Chin cough by laughing at this Expoſition? Is it not apparent not onely from the named Text, but from the precedent and ſubſequent ſtory, that the great King having heard of the beautifull and glorious Temple at Jeruſalem, and as it is likely having the particular modell of it from <hi>Ezra,</hi> or at leaſt ſome acurate deſcription, he being an able man divers wayes, pricked on perhaps with ſome ſence of Religion, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps with ſome goade of honour and kingly ambition (though
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113940:15"/>we denie not but that Gods peculiar providence was in it) to be the ſecond founder of ſuch a glorious ſtructure, the like whe reof had been but once ſeen before upon earth: and to this end ſends ſtrict Edicts to all his Lieurenants and Governours of his Provinces, to furniſh the Jews with materials for an Houſe and earthy building, if Timber, Stone and money be materials. Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> ſaith, <hi>He ſent them to build the ſpirituall Temple of Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> I perceive, Mr <hi>Dell,</hi> you have a rare gift in giving the ſence of Scripture: that can turn lime and ſand into <hi>the ſpirituall Temple of Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> could you not make the eares of an Hare to be horns, think you Mr <hi>Dell?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>ſecond force</hi> that Mr <hi>Dell</hi> draws from this place is, <hi>That Artaxerxes ought to permit this to be done, according to the Law of the Spirit of life in our) bearts,</hi> (your hearts) True, Mr. <hi>Dell,</hi> you have got all into your hearts, <hi>and not to inforce upon us any Clergy Conſtitutions. Dixit Phythagoras:</hi> Could any Expoſition come nearer to the mark? is not Mr <hi>Dell</hi> as right an Expoſitor as an Reformer? But ſtay, can it be collected from theſe words, That the King made a Decree that all the Iſraelites, Prieſts, Levires, and all, in any of his Realms which would, might go up to Jeruſolem to build and reſtore that wonderfull Structure: and according to its ancient modell, if poſſibly it might be done, and had disburſed money for the maintenance of conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall ſacrifice, the onely ſupport of the Prieſts, did he not mean that the Prieſts ſhould renew their old Clergy Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, &amp; attend the uſual accuſtomed charge of Gods Houſe; for ſo many hundred yeers put in due and care full practice by their predeceſſors? ſure he meant nothing elſe.</p>
            <p>Mr <hi>Dell</hi> ſaith that <hi>the third end of Artaxerxes his Decree was to deterre men, and ſo us, from hindering and reſiſting this work.</hi> What work? of the building of the Temple at Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem? That I beleeve it was. <hi>Immo vero aliud:</hi> no, no, another work, which Mr <hi>Dell</hi> ſaith <hi>hath his authority from Heaven.</hi> Mr
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113940:16"/>
               <hi>Dell</hi> ſcorns to go behinde the doore, he means his own work now afoot: But to put an end to this Diſcourſe, I cannot but much marvell that the man in this manner ſhould make ſo little ſcruple of making the Scripture a noſe of wax; and of ſtaulking it to all his imaginations, though never ſo farre in its own ſence eſtranged from them.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:113940:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
